Arius – Thalia
Thalia literally means “abundance,” “good cheer,” or “banquet”. It was written in verse, in order to aid memorization and popular distribution of Arius’s ideas. Fragments of this work survive in two writings of his opponent Athanasius. The first is in a report of Arius’ teaching in Orations Against the Arians, 1.5-6. This paraphrase has negative comments interspersed, so it is difficult to decide what are Arius’s words and what are comments of Athanasius (Williams 99). The second is a more direct quotation in On the Councils of Arminum and Seleucia, 15. Someone other than Athanasius, perhaps even someone sympathetic to Arius, may have compiled the quotations (Hanson 10-15, esp. 12). We used this quotation as the basis of our translation.

A recent and thorough discussion of the text, meaning, and significance of Thalia is found in Rowan Williams’ Arius: Heresy and Tradition, Revised Edition, 62-66 and 98-116. Both the translation found there, as well as that found in Hanson’s Search for the Christian Doctrine of God, 12-15, were consulted for this translation (see bibliography).

Thalia by Arius

…And so God Himself, as he really is, is inexpressible to all.
He alone has no equal, no one similar (homoios), and no one of the same glory.
We call him unbegotten, in contrast to him who by nature is begotten.
We praise him as without beginning in contrast to him who has a beginning.
We worship him as timeless, in contrast to him who in time has come to exist.

He who is without beginning made the Son a beginning of created things.
He produced him as a son for himself by begetting him.
He [the son] has none of the distinct characteristics of God’s own being (kat’ hypostasis)
For he is not equal to, nor is he of the same being (homoousios) as him.

God is wise, for he himself is the teacher of Wisdom –
Sufficient proof that God is invisible to all:
He is is invisible both to things which were made through the Son, and also to the Son himself.

I will say specifically how the invisible is seen by the Son:
by that power by which God is able to see, each according to his own measure,
the Son can bear to see the Father, as is determined

So there is a Triad, not in equal glories.
Their beings (hypostaseis) are not mixed together among themselves.
As far as their glories, one infinitely more glorious than the other.
The Father in his essence (ousia) is a foreigner to the Son, because he exists without beginning.

Understand that the Monad [eternally] was; but the Dyad was not before it came into existence.
It immediately follows that, although the Son did not exist, the Father was still God.
Hence the Son, not being [eternal] came into existence by the Father’s will,
He is the Only-begotten God, and this one is alien from [all] others

[Williams suggests a section on the Holy Spirit may have been omitted here (p. 310).]

Wisdom came to be Wisdom by the will of the Wise God.
Hence he is conceived in innumerable aspects. He is Spirit,
Power, Wisdom, God’s glory, Truth, Image, and Word.
Understand that he is also conceived of as Radiance and Light.
The one who is superior is able to beget one equal to the Son,
But not someone more important, or superior, or greater.
At God’s will the Son has the greatness and qualities that he has.
His existence from when and from whom and from then — are all from God.
He, though strong God, praises in part (ek merous) his superior .

In brief, God is inexpressible to the Son.
For he is in himself what he is, that is, indescribable,
So that the son does not comprehend any of these things or have the understanding to explain them.
For it is impossible for him to fathom the Father, who is by himself.
For the Son himself does not even know his own essence (ousia),
For being Son, his existence is most certainly at the will of the Father.

What reasoning allows, that he who is from the Father should comprehend and know his own parent?
For clearly that which has a beginning is not able to conceive of or grasp the existence of that which has no beginning.

Translation and introduction by AJW


Letter of Arius to Eusebius of Nicomedia
Incipit.	Τοῦ πατρός μου Ἀμμωνίου
Date.	c. 318
Ancient source used.	Theodoret, Church History 1.5
Modern edition used.	L. Parmentier and F. Scheidweiler, Theodoret. Kirchengeschichte, 2nd edition, GCS 44 (Berlin: Akademie Verlag, 1954)
Other ancient source.	Epiphanius, Refutation of All Heresies 69.6
Notes.	To compare this document with other lists of sympathizers with Arius, see the Arian map. In paragraph 3, Arius claims that nearly “all those of the East” agree that the Father pre-exists the Son!
(1.) To that most beloved man of God, the faithful and orthodox Eusebius, from Arius, unjustly persecuted by father Alexander because of the all-conquering truth which you, Eusebius, also are defending!

(2.) Since my father Ammonius is going to Nicomedia, it seemed reasonable and proper to greet you through him, remembering at the same time the innate love and affection which you have for the brothers on account of God and his Christ, because the bishop [Alexander] is severely ravaging and persecuting us and moving against us with every evil.  Thus he drives us out of every city like godless men, since we will not agree with his public statements:  that there was “always a God, always a Son;” “as soon as the Father, so soon the Son [existed];” “with the Father co-exists the Son unbegotten, ever-begotten, begotten without begetting;” “God neither precedes the Son in aspect or in a moment of time;” “always a God, always a Son, the Son being from God himself.”

(3.) Since Eusebius, your brother in Caesarea, and Theodotus, and Paulinus, and Athanasius, and Gregory, and Aetius and all those in the East say that God pre-exists the Son without a beginning, they have been condemned, except for Philogonius and Hellenicus and Macarius, unlearned heretics some of whom say that the Son was “spewed out”, others that he was an “emanation”, still others that he was “jointly unbegotten.”  (4.) We are not able to listen to these kinds of impieties, even if the heretics threaten us with ten thousand deaths.  But what do we say and think and what have we previously taught and do we presently teach?  — that the Son is not unbegotten, nor a part of an unbegotten entity in any way, nor from anything in existence, but that he is subsisting in will and intention before time and before the ages, full <of grace and truth,> God, the only-begotten, unchangeable. (5.) Before he was begotten, or created, or defined, or established, he did not exist.  For he was not unbegotten.   But we are persecuted because we have said the Son has a beginning but God has no beginning.  We are persecuted because of that and for saying he came from non-being.  But we said this since he is not a portion of God nor of anything in existence.  That is why we are persecuted; you know the rest.

I pray that you fare well in the Lord, remembering our tribulations, fellow-Lucianist, truly-called Eusebius [i.e. the pious one].

Translation by GLT

Other translations in New Eusebius, no. 283; NPNF2 vol. 3, p. 41;

Fragment of a letter of Eusebius of Nicomedia to Arius
Incipit	Καλῶς φρονῶν εὔχου πάντας
Date	c. 318
Ancient source	Athanasius, On the Synods 17
Modern edition used	H-G. Opitz, Athanasius Werke, band 2 (Berlin: De Gruyter, 1940).
And Eusebius of Nicomedia in addition wrote thus to Arius:

Since you think properly, pray that everyone will think that way. For it is clear to all that the thing which is made did not exist before it came into being; but rather what came into being has a beginning to its existence.

Translation by GLT

Other translations in Hanson, p. 31; NPNF2 vol. 4, p. 459


Summary of a letter issued by a council in Palestine
Incipit	[Ὡς δὲ οὐδὲν ἧττον]
Date	c. 321/2
Ancient source	Sozomen, Church History 1.15.11
Modern edition used	J. Bidez and G.C. Hansen, Sozomenus: Kirchengeschichte GCS 50 (Berlin: Akademie Verlag, 1960)
Since Alexander was not willing to give way in his zeal for the correct understanding of God, Arius sent messengers to Paulinus, bishop of Tyre, to Eusebius Pamphilus, who presided over the church of Cæsarea in Palestine, and to Patrophilus, bishop of Scythopolis. He solicited permission for himself and for his adherents, as they had previously attained the rank of priests, to form the people who were with them into a church. For it was the custom in Alexandria, as it still is in the present day, that all the churches should be under one bishop, but that each priest should have his own church, in which to assemble the people. These three bishops, concurring with the others who were assembled in Palestine, granted Arius’ petition.

They permitted him to assemble the people as before, but commanded Arius to submit to Alexander and to continually strive to be restored to peace and fellowship with him.

Translation from NPNF2 vol. 2, p.252, adapted by AJW


Confession of faith from Arius and his followers to Bishop Alexander of Alexandria
Incipit	Ἡ πίστις ἡμῶν
Date	c. 320
Ancient source used (paragraphs 1-5)	Athanasius, On the Synods 16
Modern edition used	H-G. Opitz, Athanasius Werke, band 2 (Berlin: De Gruyter, 1940).
Other ancient sources (paragraph 1-5)	Epiphanius, Refutation of All Heresies 69.7-8
Hilary, On the Trinity 4.12f. 6.5f.
Ancient source (paragraph 6)	Epiphanius, Refutation of All Heresies 69.8
Modern edition used:	K. Holl, Epiphanius: Panarion GCS 37 (Leipzig: Hinrichs, 1933)
Note	The creed given in this document is quoted by Eusebius of Caesarea in his letter to Alexander of Alexandria (Urk. 7). Lewis Ayres points out the difficultly with this document: “The question here turns on whether or not one reads this letter as conciliatory! (Nicaea and its Legacy [Oxford 2004], p. 17 note 16).
Williams notes that the similarity of the creed to the creed of the council of Antioch (Urk. 18) gives credence to Arius claim that he is drawing on a faith learned from the forefathers. (Williams, p. 96)
(1.) The Priests and Deacons to Our Blessed Father and Bishop, Alexander; greetings in the Lord.

(2.) Our faith from our forefathers, which also we learned from you, Blessed Father, is this: We acknowledge One God, alone unbegotten, alone everlasting, alone without beginning, alone true, alone having immortality, alone wise, alone good, alone sovereign, judge, governor, and provider of all, unalterable and unchangeable, just and good, God of the Law and the Prophets and the New Testament; who begat an only-begotten Son before time and the ages, through whom he made both the ages [Heb 1:2] and all that was made; who begot Him not in appearance, but in reality; and that he made him subsist at his own will, unalterable and unchangeable, the perfect creature (ktisma) of God, but not as one of the creatures; offspring, but not as one of the other things begotten; (3.) nor as Valentinus pronounced that the offspring of the Father was an emanation (probolē); nor as the Manicheans taught that the offspring was a one-in-essence-portion (meros homoousion) of the Father; nor as Sabellius, dividing the Monad, speaks of a Son-Father; nor as Hieracas speaks of one torch [lit] from another, or as a lamp divided into two; nor that he who existed before was later generated or created anew into a Son, as you yourself, O blessed father, have often condemned both in church services and in council meetings; but, as we say, he was created at the will of God, before time and before the ages, and came to life and being from the Father, and the glories which coexist in him are from the Father.

(4.) For when giving to him [the Son] the inheritance of all things [Heb 1:2], the Father did not deprive himself of what he has without beginning in himself; for he is the source of all things. Thus there are three subsisting realities (hypostaseis). And God, being the cause of all that happens, is absolutely alone without beginning; but the Son, begotten apart from time by the Father, and created (ktistheis) and founded before the ages, was not in existence before his generation, but was begotten apart from time before all things, and he alone came into existence (hypestē) from the Father. For he is neither eternal nor co-eternal nor co-unbegotten with the Father, nor does he have his being together with the Father, as some speak of relations, introducing two unbegotten beginnings. But God is before all things as monad and beginning of all. Therefore he is also before the Son, as we have learned also from your public preaching in the church.

(5.) Therefore he thus has his being from God; and glories, and life, and all things have been given over to him; in this way God is his beginning. For he is over him, as his God and being before him. But if the expressions from him [Rom. 11:36] and from the womb [Ps. 109:3 (LXX), 110:3 English] and I came from the Father, and I have come [John 16:28], are understood by some to mean that he is part of him [the Father], one in essence or as an emanation, then the Father is, according to them, compounded and divisible and alterable and material, and, as far as their belief goes, the incorporeal God endures a body.

(6.) I pray that you fare well in the Lord, blessed father. Arius; the priests Aethales, Achilles, Carpones, Sarmatas and Arius; the deacons Euzoios, Lucius, Julius, Menas, Helladius, and Gaius; the bishops Secundas of the Pentapolis, Theonas of Libya, and Pistus whom the Arians [later] set up [as bishop] at Alexandria.

Section 1-5: Translation from Athanasius (NPNF2 vol. 4, p. 458), adapted by GLT

Section 6: Translation by GLT

Other translation in New Eusebius, no. 284


Emperor Constantine to Arius
Incipit:	Κακὸς ἑρμηνεὺς
Date:	333
Ancient source used	Athanasius, Defense of the Nicene Definition 40
Modern edition used	H-G. Opitz, Athanasius Werke, band 2 (Berlin: De Gruyter, 1935).
Other ancient sources	Socrates, Church History 1.9.30
Gelasius, Church History 3.19.1
Constantine Augustus to Arius and to Arians.

(1.) A wicked interpreter is really an image and a statue of the Devil. For as skilled sculptors mould him for an incitement to deception, as if cunningly contriving a goodly appearance of beauty for him, who by nature is absolutely most base, that he may destroy miserable persons by offering error to them, in the same way, I think, must act this fellow, to whom only this appears to be worthy of zeal: namely, to proffer profusely the poisons of his own effrontery. (2.) Therefore he introduces a belief of unbelief – new and never yet at any time seen since men have been born. Wherefore truly that does not seem at variance from the truth, which long ago was described distinctly by the divine saying: “They are trusty for evil.” (3.) For why can anyone say this: that he who no longer desires to find any aid for alleviation has lost the grace of taking advice? Why, then, do I say: “Christ, Christ, Lord, Lord!”? Why in the world do bandits injure us daily? A certain harsh and violent audacity stands before us; it roars, gnashing its teeth, deformed by dishonor, and wounded by manifold accusations. (4.) Of course, it, just as if scattered by certain storms and waves of evils, in the law and the proclamation about you vomits pernicious words and in writing produces these, which you, who do not at all coexist with the Eternal Father of your origin, have defined by cognition about yourself. In short, it collects and gathers certain terrible and lawless impieties, now indeed agitating tongues, now again uplifted by enthusiasm for miserable persons, whom, when present for security, it deceives and destroys.

(5.) But now I wish to examine the character of its chief proponent. For what says he? He says, “Either let us hold that, of which already we have been made possessors, or let it be done, just as we ourselves desire.” He has fallen and in these matters he has fallen dead; he says: “By treachery or cleverness of knavery” – it makes no difference. He considers holy only what has crept into him through base thought. He says: “We have the masses.” (6.) Indeed, I myself shall advance a little farther, that I may become a spectator of those wars of insanity. I myself, I said, shall advance, I who have been accustomed to end wars of senseless men. Come now Ares Arius, there is need for shields. Do not do this, we beg; at least, then, let Aphrodite’s intercourse detain you. But really, would that, as you seem to fashion the finest things for the masses, so it would be your part to abound in piety toward Christ! (7.) Look, I come again as a suppliant and, though powerful in weapons in respect to the whole populace, I do not wish to fight; but fortified by Christ’s faith, I desire you both to be cured and to heal others. (8.) Why, therefore, do you say that you do these things, which befit not your character? But with what peace, tell me, or encompassed with what abundance, but rather, advanced with what rashness? Oh, audacity worthy to be destroyed by thunderbolts! For hear what he, writing with a pen distilling poison, recently has explained to me. He says: “Thus we believe.” Then I suppose, having added I know not what certain things somehow swaggeringly and quite accurately elaborated, he, going farther, left unsaid nothing at all of bitterness, but he opened the whole – as someone may say – treasury of madness. He says: “We are expelled and they take from us permission to be admitted.” (9.) But this is not at all apposite to the matter; turn your mind to what follows, for I shall use his words. He says: “We ask that, if the bishop of Alexandria remains in the same opinion, hereafter it be granted to us – according to the law’s arrangement- to celebrate the lawful and indispensable services to God.” (10.) Oh, terrible shamelessness, which ought to be refuted thoroughly by the zeal for truth! For what has happened to please him, this has been marked by conciseness of expression. What do you say, foolish one? Do you prepare to construct the disease of your savage thought against me as a discord, which is specious in our sight? And do you hasten to destroy the persons involved with your evil? (11.) “What, then,” you say, “Shall I do, if none deems me worthy to be admitted?” For this you often shout from a profane throat. But I shall speak against you: Where have you shown a clear mark and proof of your intelligence? And this you ought to have disclosed and to have established clearly for gods and men- and especially when poisonous serpents even then are by nature more savage, when they know that they themselves are found in recesses of dens.

(12.) But that is indeed quite urbane of him: that quite eagerly, just as if under a certain mask of modesty, he pretends silence. You indeed show yourself tame and submissive by the artifice of pretence; you escape the notice of many, when you within are full of countless evils and plots. But, oh, wretchedness! As the Devil has desired, so he had made Arius a manufactory of iniquity for us. (13.) Advancing now, tell me the mark of your faith and indeed not at all be silent. Oh, you possessor of a mouth perverted and a nature quickly roused to wickedness! “Do you talk of one God?” You have me of the same opinion; think so. Do you say that the “the Word of his essence is the Word without beginning and without end?” I acquiesce in this; believe so. (14.) If you add anything further, this I abrogate. If you join anything to an impious separation, I confess that I neither see nor perceive this. If you accept “the body’s lodging in respect to the administration of divine operations,” I do not reject it. If you say that “the spirit of eternity was born in the pre-eminent Word,” I receive it. Who has known the Father, unless he who comes from the Father? Whom has the Father known, unless him whom he has begotten from himself eternally and without beginning? You think that you ought to substitute a “foreign hypostasis,” believing doubtless badly; I know that the plentitude of the Fathers and the Sons pre-eminent and all-pervading power is one substance. (15.) If, therefore, you detract from him, from whom not yet ever anything has been able to be separated even by idle talkers’ process of thinking, you pave the way for the marks of addition and, in short, you determine the signs of inquiries for him, to whom he had given entire eternity for himself and uncorrupted intelligence and his assigned belief in immortality through both himself and the Church. Discard then this silly transgression of the law, you witty and sweet-voiced fellow, singing evil songs for the unbelief of senseless persons. (16.) Quite fittingly the Devil has subverted you by his own wickedness; and perhaps this seems pleasant to certain persons (for thus you have persuaded yourself). But it is in every way a destructive evil. (17.) Come now, having departed from your occupation with absurdities, listen, good Arius, for I discourse with you. Do you not understand that you have been barred publicly fro God’s church? You are lost (be well assured), unless, having regard for yourself, you condemn your present folly. But you will say that the masses act with you and dispel your anxieties.

(18.) Lend your ears and listen a little, impious Arius, and understand your folly. O God, protector of all, may you be well – disposed to what is being said, if it should admit of faith! For I, your man, holding to your propitious providence, from the very ancient Greek and Roman writing shall demonstrate clearly Arius’ madness, which has been prophesied and predicted three thousand years ago by the Erythraean sibyl. (19.) For she indeed says: “Woe to you, Libya, situated in maritime regions, for there shall come to you a time, in which with the people and your daughters you must be compelled to undergo a terrible and cruel and very difficult crisis, from which a judgment both of faith and of piety in respect to all persons will be given, but you will decline to extreme ruin, for you have dared to engulf the receptacle of celestial flowers and to mangle it with a bite and you have polluted it with iron teeth.” (20.) What then, knave? Where in the world do you admit that you are now? There, obviously; for I have your letters, which you have scraped with the pen of madness toward me, in which you say that all the Libyan populace is of the same opinion with you – doubtless in regard to salvation. But if you shall deny that this is so, I now call God to witness that truly I send to Alexandria – that you may perish more quickly – the Erythraean Sibyl’s very ancient tablet, composed in the Greek tongue. (21.) Are you, then, really blameless, gallows rogue? Have you not, then, really perished, sorry fellow, surrounded by such great horror? We know, we know your undertaking; what kind of anxiety, what kind of fear troubles you, wretched and miserable person, has not escaped our notice. Oh, the dullness of your wits, you profane person, who do not restrain your soul’s sickness and helplessness, who undermine the truth by varied discourses. And, since you are such, you are not ashamed to disparage us, now refuting (as you indeed suppose), now again admonishing (as if superior in faith and in discourses), a person from whom, of course, wretched persons are eager to procure aid for themselves, (22.) although they ought neither to associate with such a person nor, in short, to address him, unless anyone thinks that in this one’s rotten words and meters is stored the hope of living uprightly. (23.) But this is not so; indeed, in very truth it is far from it. Oh, your folly, as many of you as associate with this person! What madness, then, has compelled you to endure this one’s bitter tongue and sight?

(24.) Well; but now I shall proceed by my discourse against you yourself, you fool in respect to your soul, you wordy one in respect to your tongue, you infidel in respect to your wits. Grant to me a field for discussion (I do not say one wide-spreading and fit for horsemanship, but indeed a circle easy to trace, not one decayed, but firm and solid by nature), you truly profane and basest and dissembling person. For I am excited to say these things; but rather, having fasted a noose around you and having entangled you by discussion, I shall set you in the midst, that all the people may observe well your worthlessness. (25.) But I shall proceed now to the matter itself. Certainly, my hands have been cleansed. Let us proceed, then, to invoke God with prayers: rather, wait a little while. Tell me, you very hasty one, what God will you invoke for aid? For I cannot keep myself quiet. (26.) O Lord, you who have the supreme authority over all things, O Father of singular power, because of this profane person your Church receives both reproaches and griefs and also both wounds and pains. Arius now adapts for you a place (and very cleverly indeed), in which, constituting – as I think – a synod for himself, by the law of adoption he procures and preserves your Son Christ, born from you, the bringer of our aid. (27.) Hear, I entreat you, this marvelous faith. He thinks that you, Lord, the principle of motion, are demoted from your place. He dares to circumscribe you by a circle of a defined seat. For where is not your presence? Or where do all persons not perceive your activity from your all-pervading laws? For you yourself encompass all things and it is not right to think of either a place or anything else outside you. Thus your power with activity is infinite. (28.) Do you, God, then hear; do you, all the people, pay attention. For this fellow is shameless and useless, who, having progressed to the height both of wickedness and likewise of lawlessness, pretends piety. (29.) He says: “Away! I do not wish God to appear to be subject to suffering of outrages, and on this account I suggest and fabricate wondrous things indeed in respect to faith: that God, when he had made the newly born and the newly created essence of Christ, prepared aid for himself, as it seems indeed to me. For what you have taken from him, this you have made less.” Is this, then, your faith, spoiler and destroyer? (30.) According to hypothesis do you accept as a figment him who has condemned the figments of the heathen? Do you call foreign and – as it were – a servant of duties him who without reflection and reasoning, in that he coexists with the Father’s eternity, perfected all things? Now adapt, if indeed you dare, adapt I say, to God both precaution and hope of what will happen, also reflection, reasoning, declaration and articulation of considered judgment, and, in short, delight, laughter, grief. (31.) What then, do you say, one more wretched than the wretched, oh, truly an adviser of evil? Understand, if you can, that in your very knavery you are destroyed as a villain.

(32.) He says: “Christ has suffered for us.” But I already have said that he was sent in the form of a body. He says:” Truly; but it is necessary that we seem not to make him less in any respect.” Then, mediator of wild beasts, when you say these things, are you not mad and clearly raving? For, look, the world itself is a form or at any rate is a figure; and the stars indeed have produced their images; and, in short, the spirit of this spheroidal circle is an appearance of existing things and – as it were – a figuration. And, nevertheless, God is present everywhere. Where, therefore, in God are outrages? Or in what respect is God made less? (33.) Oh, you patricide of equity! Consider, then conjecturing from yourself, and conclude, if this seems to be a sin, that God is present in Christ. That fellow, then, has known well the disgracefulness of his talk and not slowly he brought punishment on himself. Moreover doubtless daily sins are committed in the world – and, nevertheless, God is present and punishments are not delayed. In this respect, then, what diminution is made in his power’s magnitude, if punishments are perceived everywhere? Nothing, I think. (34.) For the mind of the world is through God; through him is all stability; through him is all justice; the faith of Christ is without beginning from him. In short, God’s law is Christ, having through him boundlessness and also endlessness.

(35.) But you appear to take thought from your own self. Oh, excessive madness! Turn now to your own destruction the Devil’s sword. See, then, all see how he, when pierced by the viper’s bite, now produces lamentable sounds; how his veins and muscles, when attacked next by the venom, evoke terrible pangs; how his whole emaciated body has wasted away, is full of squalor and filth and lamentations and pallor and horror and myriad ills, and has withered frightfully; how odious and dirty in his thicket of hair; how wholly half-dead and already exhausted in its glance; how bloodless in his face and wasted under anxiety; how all things converging at the same time upon him – frenzy and madness and vanity – through the long time of the calamity have made him both boorish and bestial. (36.) For example, he does not perceive in what bad state he is. He says: “I am exalted with delight and I jump, leaping with joy, and I soar.” And again quite youthfully he says: “Well, we have perished.” (37.) And this indeed is true, for to you alone wickedness bountifully has supplied its own enthusiasms; and what had been bought for a great price, this has been given very easily to you. Come now, tell, where are your august consuls? Wash yourself, then, in the Nile, if possible, you fellow full of absurd insensibility; and indeed you have hastened to disturb the whole world by your impieties. (38.) Do you understand that I, the man of God, already know all things? But I am in doubt whether I ought to remain or to depart, for I no longer am able to look upon this person and I am ashamed at sin, Arius. You have brought us into the light; you have hurled yourself, wretched one, into darkness. This has appeared the end of your labors.

(39.) But again I return thither. You say that there is a multitude of persons wandering about you. That is likely, I think; and take them, then, I say, take them, for they have given themselves to be eaten by wolves and by lions. However, each one of these, oppressed by additional payment of ten capitation taxes and by the expenses of these, immediately will sweat, unless, running as speedily as possible to the salvation-bringing Church, he has chosen the peace of love through affection for harmony. (40.) For no longer will they, condemned for wicked complicity, be deceived by you nor will they, entangled in your abominable investigations, continue to perish absolutely. Your sophisms are clear and known to all persons, at all events for the future. Nor indeed will you yourself be able to accomplish anything, but in vain will you contrive, counterfeiting both fairness and gentleness of discourses and donning externally – so to speak – a mask of simplicity. In vain will be all your artifice, for straightway the truth will circumvent you, straightway the rain of divine power – so to speak – will quench your flames. (41.) And, of course, the functions of the public services will overtake your associates and likeminded persons, who have become liable to the senate, unless indeed they, fleeing as speedily as possible association with you, accept in exchange the uncorrupted faith. (42.) But do you, iron-hearted man, give to me an evidence of your purpose, if you have faith in yourself, and be strong in the strength of faith, and you absolutely will have a pure conscience. Come to me, come, I say, to a man of God; believe that by my interrogations I shall search your heart’s secrets; and, if any madness shall seem to be in you, I, after having invoked divine grace, shall heal you fairer than a model. But if you shall appear to be healthy in respect to spiritual matters, I, after I have recognized the light of the truth in you, shall give thanks to God and I shall rejoice with myself for the sake of piety.

(43.) And by another hand: May God guard you, beloved.

And this was executed by Syncletius and Gaudentius, magistrians, when Paterius was prefect of Egypt, and was read in the palace.

Translation from Coleman-Norton, P.R., Roman State and Christian Church, London: Society for Promoting Christian Knowledge (SPCK) 1966, #67. Used with permission.


Part of an edict against Arius and his followers
Incipit	Τοὺς πονηροὺς καὶ ἀσεβεῖς
Date	333
Ancient source used	Athanasius, Defense of the Nicene Definition 39
Modern edition used	H-G. Opitz, Athanasius Werke, vol. 2.1 (Berlin: De Gruyter, 1940).
Other ancient Greek sources	Socrates, Church History 1.9.30 and Gelasius, Church History 2.36.1
Ancient Syriac sources	2 manuscripts: Brit. Mus. Add. 14,528 and Vatican Borg. Syr. 82
Modern edition of Syriac	Fredrich Schulthess, “Die syrischen Kanones der Synoden von Nicaea bis Chalcedon.” Abhandlungen der Königlichen Gesellschaft der Wissenschaften zu Göttingen, Philologisch-Historische Klasse N.F. 10, no. 2 (Berlin: Weidmannsche Buchhandlung, 1908) pp. 1-2
(1.) The great and victorious Constantine Augustus to the bishops and laity:

Since Arius is an imitator of the wicked and the ungodly, it is only right that he should suffer the same dishonor as they. Porphyry, who was hostile to anyone who feared God, composed a book which transgressed against our religion, and has found a suitable reward: namely that he has been disgraced from that time onward, his reputation is completely terrible, and his ungodly writings have been destroyed. In the same way it seems appropriate that Arius and those of like mind with Arius should from now on be called Porphyrians, so that their name is taken from those whose ways they have imitated. (2.) In addition, if any writing composed by Arius should be found, it should be handed over to the flames, so that not only will the wickedness of his teaching be obliterated, but nothing will be left even to remind anyone of him. And I hereby make a public order, that if someone should be discovered to have hidden a writing composed by Arius, and not to have immediately brought it forward and destroyed it by fire, his penalty shall be death. As soon as he is discovered in this offense, he shall be submitted for capital punishment.

And in another hand:

God will watch over you, beloved brothers.

Translation by AJW

Other translation in Socrates (NPNF2 vol. 2, p. 14)


Arius and Euzoius to the Emperor Constantine

Incipit	Καθὼς προσέταξεν ἡ θεοφιλής
Date	End of 327
Ancient source used	Socrates, Church History 1.26.2
Modern edition used	W. Bright, Socrates’ ecclesiastical history, 2nd edition (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1893)
Other ancient source	Sozomen, Church History 2.27.6-10
Arius and Euzoïus, to our most reverent and pious lord, Emperor Constantine.

(1.) In accord with the command of your devout piety, sovereign lord, we declare our faith, and in writing profess before God that we and our adherents believe as follows:

(2.) We believe in one God the Father Almighty, and in the Lord Jesus Christ his Son, who was begotten of him before all ages, God the Word through whom all things were made, both things in heaven and on earth; who descended, and became human, and suffered, and rose again, ascended into heaven, and will again come to judge the living and the dead. (3.) We believe also in the Holy Spirit, and in the resurrection of the flesh, and in the life of the coming age, and in the kingdom of the heavens, and in one catholic church of God, extending from one end of the earth to the other. (4.) This faith we have received from the holy gospels, in which the Lord says to his disciples: “Go and teach all nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit.” If we do not so believe and do not truly receive the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit, as the whole catholic church and the holy Scriptures teach (in which we believe in every respect), may God judge us both now, and in the coming judgment. (5.) Wherefore we (who have been consecrated to the ministry, and hold the faith and opinions of the church and of the holy Scriptures) encourage your piety, most devout emperor, that we may be reunited to our mother, the church, by your peace-loving and devoted piety, avoiding all superfluous questions and disputes. Then both we and the whole church will be at peace and will offer in common our accustomed prayers for your tranquil reign, and also for your whole family.

Translation from Socrates (NPNF2 vol. 2, p. 28), adapted by AJW

Other translations in New Eusebius, no. 295 and Sozomen (NPNF2 vol. 2, p. 277)

Emperor Constantine to Arius
Reference numbers	Urk. 29
Doc. 33
CPG 2040)
Incipit	Πάλαι μὲν ἐδηλώθη
Date	27th Nov. 327
Ancient source	Socrates, HE 1.25.7
Modern edition used	W. Bright, Socrates’ ecclesiastical history, 2nd edition (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1893)
Constantine the Great Augustus, to Arius.

It was made known to you in your stubbornness some time ago, that you might want to come to our headquarters, so that perhaps you could enjoy the privilege of seeing us. We are quite amazed that you did not do so immediately. Therefore, now board a public (official) vehicle, and hasten to come to our court. This way, once you have been in our company and obtained favor from us, you may be able to return to your own country. May God protect you, beloved.

Dated the twenty-seventh of November.

Translation by AJW



Documents of the Early Arian Controversy – Emperor Constantine to Alexander of Alexandria and Arius

Incipit	Διπλῆν μοι γεγενῆσθαι
Date	October 324
Ancient source used	Eusebius, Life of Constantine 2.64-72
Modern edition used	F. Winkelmann, Eusebius Werke, Band 1.1: Über das Leben des Kaisers Konstantin, GCS vol. 7, 7.1. (Berlin: Akademie Verlag, 1975)
Other ancient source (paragraphs 6-15)	Socrates, Church History 1.7;
Gelasius, Church History 2.4
Note on recipients	Stuart G. Hall argues that this letter was actually written to the Council of Antioch in 325, and that Eusebius, who would rather forget that council, changed the recipients in his account of the letter.1 Parvis has critiqued his argument to say that the letter was certainly meant for a general audience of eastern bishops, but not for the Council of Antioch specifically.2 This could also explain how Eusebius has a copy.
1 Stuart G. Hall, “Some Constantinian Documents in the Vita Constantini,” Constantine: History and Historiography, eds. Samuel N. C. Lieu and Dominic Montserrat (New York 1998), pp. 86-104

2 Sarah Parvis (see Abbreviations page), p. 77, note 172.

The Victor Constantine, the Great Augustus, to Alexander and Arius.

(1.) I call God to witness, as is fitting, who is the helper of my endeavors and the preserver of all men, that I had a twofold reason for undertaking this duty which I have now performed. My design then was first to bring the various beliefs formed by all nations about God to a condition of settled uniformity. Secondly I hoped to restore to health the civil liberties of the empire, then suffering under the malignant power of an angry tyrant. Keeping these objects in view, I sought to accomplish the one by thought, which is hidden from the eye, while the other I tried to rectify by the power of military authority. For I was aware that, if I should succeed in establishing, according to my hopes, a common harmony of sentiment among all the servants of God, the general course of affairs would also experience a change corresponding to the pious desires of all.

(2.) So when I found that an intolerable spirit of mad folly had overcome the whole of Africa, through the influence of those who with heedless frivolity had presumed to divide the religion of the people into diverse sects, I was anxious to stop the course of this disorder. After I had removed the common enemy of mankind [Licinius] who had interposed his lawless sentence which prohibited your holy synods, I could discover no other remedy equal to the occasion, except to send some of you churchmen to aid in restoring mutual harmony among the disputants.

(3.) I naturally believed that you in the East would be the first to promote the salvation of other nations, since the power of Divine light and the law of sacred worship, which proceeded in the first instance through the favor of God, from the bosom, as it were, of the East, have illumined the world by their sacred radiance. So I resolved with all energy of thought and diligence of enquiry to seek your aid. As soon, as I had secured my decisive victory and unquestioned triumph over my enemies, my first enquiry was concerning that object which I felt to be of paramount interest and importance.

(4.) But, O glorious Providence of God! How deep a wound did not my ears only, but my very heart receive when it was reported that divisions existed among yourselves more grievous still than those which continued in that country [Africa, i.e. the Donatist schism]! You, through whose aid I had hoped to procure a remedy for the errors of others, are in a state which needs healing even more than theirs. And yet, now that I have made a careful enquiry into the origin and foundation of these differences, I have found the cause to be of a truly insignificant character, and quite unworthy of such fierce contention. I feel compelled to address you in this letter, and to appeal at the same time to your unity and discernment. I call on Divine Providence to assist me in the task, while I interrupt your dissension as a minister of peace. (5.) I have hope for success: Even in a great disagreement I might expect with the help of the higher Power, to be able without difficulty, by a judicious appeal to the pious feelings of those who hear me, to recall them to a better spirit. How can I help but to expect a far easier and more speedy resolution of this difference, when the cause which hinders general harmony of sentiment is intrinsically trifling and of little importance?

(6.) I understand that the origin of the present controversy is this. When you, Alexander, demanded of the priests what opinion they each maintained respecting a certain passage in Scripture, or rather, I should say, that you asked them something connected with an unprofitable question. You then, Arius, inconsiderately insisted on what ought never to have been speculated about at all, or if pondered, should have been buried in profound silence. Hence it was that a dissension arose between you, fellowship was withdrawn, and the holy people were rent into diverse factions, no longer preserving the unity of the one body. (7.) And so I now ask you both to show an equal degree of consideration for the other, and to receive the advice which your fellow-servant impartially gives. What then is this advice? It was wrong in the first instance to propose such questions as these, and also wrong to reply to them when they were presented. (8.) For those points of discussion are not commanded by the authority of any law, but are rather the product of an argumentative spirit which is encouraged by the idle useless talk of leisure. Even though they may be intended merely as an intellectual exercise, they ought certainly to be confined to the region of our own thoughts, and not hastily produced in the popular assemblies, nor unadvisedly entrusted to the ears of the general public. For how very few are there able either accurately to comprehend, or adequately to explain subjects so sublime and difficult to comprehend in their nature? Or, granting that one were fully competent for this, how many people will he convince? Or again, who in dealing with questions involving such subtle distinctions as these can be sure he is not dangerously departing from the truth in some point? We ourselves may be unable, through the weakness of our natural abilities, to give a clear explanation of the subject before us, or, on the other hand, our hearers understanding may prevent them from arriving at an accurate understanding of what we say. Lest that be the case, it is our obligation to be sparing with our words, so that neither of these situations will cause the people to be reduced either to blasphemy or to schism.

(9.) Now forgive one another for both the careless question and the ill-considered answer. The cause of your difference has not been any of the leading doctrines or precepts of the Divine law, nor has any new heresy respecting the worship of God arisen among you. You are really of one and the same judgment; and so it is fitting for you to join in communion and fellowship. (10.) As long as you continue to contend about these small and very insignificant questions, it is not fitting that so large a portion of God’s people should be under the direction of your judgment, since you are thus divided between yourselves. In my opinion, it is not merely unbecoming, but positively evil, that such should be the case. Let me arouse your minds by the following little illustration. You know that philosophers, though they all adhere to one system, are yet frequently at issue on certain points, and differ, perhaps, in their degree of knowledge. Yet they are brought back to harmony of opinion by the uniting power of their common teachings. If this be true, is it not far more reasonable that you, who are the ministers of the Supreme God, should be of one mind in the profession of the same religion? Let us still more thoughtfully and with closer attention examine what I have said, and see whether it be right: On the ground of some trifling and foolish verbal difference between ourselves, should brothers assume towards each other the attitude of enemies? Should the honorable synod be torn in two by profane disunion, because of you who wrangle together on points so trivial and altogether unessential? This is vulgar, and more characteristic of childish ignorance, than consistent with the wisdom of priests and sensible men. (11.) Let us withdraw ourselves with a good will from these temptations of the devil. Our great God and our common Savior has granted us all the same light. Permit me, who am his servant, to successfully bring my task to conclusion, under the direction of his providence, that I may be enabled, through my exhortations, diligence, and earnest warning, to recall his people to communion and fellowship. (12.) You have, as I said, only one faith, and one opinion about our religion, and the Divine commandment in all its parts imposes upon us all the duty of maintaining a spirit of peace. Because of this, you should not let the circumstance which has led to a slight difference between you cause any division or schism among you, since it does not affect the validity of the whole. (13.) I say this without in any way desiring to force you to a complete unity of judgment in regard to this truly idle question, whatever its real nature may be. For the dignity of your synod can be preserved, and the communion of your whole body can be maintained unbroken, no matter how wide a difference exists among you about unimportant matters. We are not all like-minded on every subject, nor is there such a thing as one universal disposition and judgment.

(14.) As far, then, as regards Divine Providence, let there be one faith, and one understanding among you, one united judgment concerning God. But as to your subtle disputations on questions of little or no significance, though you may be unable to harmonize in opinion, such differences should be confined to your own private minds and thoughts. And now, let the preciousness of common affection, let faith in the truth, let the honor due to God and to the observance of his law remain immovably among you. Resume your mutual feelings of friendship, love, and respect. Restore to the people their customary embraces; and you yourselves purify your souls, as it were, and once more acknowledge one another. For it often happens that when a reconciliation is effected by the removal of the causes of hostility, friendship becomes even sweeter than it was before.

(15.) Restore me then my quiet days, and untroubled nights, that the joy of undimmed light, the delight of a tranquil life, may be my portion from here on. Otherwise I will be forced to mourn with constant tears, and I will not be able to pass the remainder of my days in peace. While the people of God, whose fellow-servant I am, are so divided among themselves by an unreasonable and wicked spirit of contention, how is it possible that I shall be able to maintain a tranquil mind? And I will give you a proof how great my sorrow has been in this regard. Not long ago I visited Nicomedia, and had intended to proceed immediately from that city to the East. It was while I was hurrying towards you, and had already finished the greater part of the journey, that the news of this matter reversed my plan, so that I would not be forced to see with my own eyes that which I felt myself scarcely able even to hear. So open for me by your unity of judgment that road to the regions of the East which your dissensions have closed to me, and permit me speedily to see you and all other peoples rejoicing together. Render due acknowledgment to God in the language of praise and thanksgiving for the restoration of general peace and liberty to all.

Translation from NPNF2 vol. 1, pp. 515-8, adapted by AJW

Sections 6-15 also found translated in NPNF2 vol. 2, pp. 6-7 and New Eusebius, no. 287


Fragment of a letter from Priest George to the Arians
Incipit	τί μέμφεσθε Ἀλεξάνδρῳ τῷ πάπᾳ
Date	c. 322
Ancient source	Athanasius, On the Synods 17.6
Modern edition used	H-G. Opitz, Athanasius Werke, band 2 (Berlin: De Gruyter, 1940).
And [George] wrote to the Arians:

Why do you find fault with Bishop Alexander for saying that the Son is from the Father?  For you also should not be afraid to say that the Son is from God.  For if the Apostle wrote ‘All things are from God’ [1 Cor 11:12], (though all things have clearly been made from nothing), and if also the Son is also a creature (κτίσμα), and he too was made, then the Son can can be said to be “from God,” just as all things are said to be “from God.”

Translation by AJW

Also translated in Hanson, p. 44